目前为止生命的故事里,
So far on life story
我们见到动物面对童年的挑战
we have seen animals face
the challenges of childhood...
成长
grow up
寻找他们在成年世界里的一席之地
..find their place
in the adult world...
赢得个伴侣
..and win a mate.
现在 在生命故事里的最终章节里
Now, in the final chapter
of Life Story,
动物们成了父母
animals become parents.
他们的后代将成为未来的遗产
Their offspring will be
their legacy to the future
假如他们能够成功哺育它们的话
if they can raise them successfully.
在自然界里面没有什么能比
There is no stronger bond in nature
父母和他们的后代间更紧的联系了
than that between some parents
and their offspring.
刚过森林里的倭黑猩猩
Bonobos in the Congo rainforest.
他们是我们最亲近的亲戚
They are our closest relatives.
这个母亲的孩子将托付于她一生
This mother's youngster
is a lifelong commitment.
他在五岁之前将完全依靠他母亲
He will be totally dependent on her
until he's five years old.
并且他将在她剩余的生命里支持她
And she will continue to support him
for the rest of her life.
他们的关系或将持续三十年
Their relationship may last
30 years.
尽管他们之间的羁绊
Although the length of her
commitment is longer
比其他大部分的动物要长
than for most animals,
她同样承受着与其他父母同样巨大的挑战
she shares with many other parents
the same great challenge -
使她的后代儿女们健康安全
keeping her offspring healthy and
safe.
父母和年轻人之间的联系将会遭受各种各样的测试
The bond between parents and young
will be tested in many ways,
有些是次要的
有些则是生或死的区别
some minor,
and some a matter of life or death.
一个母亲的照料可能在孩子出生很早之前就开始了
And a parent's commitment
may begin long before birth.
在大珊瑚礁遥远的北方一角
The remote northern tip
of the Great Barrier Reef.
在海里度过三十年以后
After over three decades at sea,
这只雌性绿蠵龟即将回到
this female green turtle is
returning to the island
她产卵的海滩上
where she hatched.
轮到她产卵了
It's time for her to lay eggs...
但他们只会在干燥的沙地上产卵
..but they will only hatch
on dry land.
她必须离开凉爽的海洋 并且进入一个陌生的世界
She must leave the cool sea
and enter an alien world.
没有了水的支持
Without the support of water,
她感受到了重力的压力
she feels the full force of gravity.
她的蹼  专门用来游泳的
Her flippers,
so effective for swimming,
在沙地上几乎无用武之地
are almost useless on land.
但无论如何  他都必须拖着她笨重的身躯到海滩上
But, nonetheless, she has to haul
her great weight up the beach
并且远离潮汐的范围内
and get beyond
the reach of the tide.
乌龟们计算到达的时间
Turtles time their arrival
所以他们可以在凉爽的黑暗里
so that their laborious journey
up the beach
完成辛苦的旅程
is made in the cool of darkness.
在某一个夜晚里
On any one night,
三千只雌性绿蠵龟会聚集挤在这个岛屿来挖她们的巢
3,000 female turtles may crowd
this island to dig their nests.
现在留下后代的压力可能会使她丢掉她的性命
Now her compulsion to leave
offspring may cost her her life.
退去的潮水暴露了岩岸  一墙崎岖不平的岩石
The receding tide has exposed
the reef, a wall of jagged rock.
看起来就像不可翻越的屏障
It looks
an almost impassable barrier
对于一只精疲力竭的乌龟而言
for an already exhausted turtle.
但她不能等到潮水再次到来
But she can't wait for the tide
to return
因为很快这个岛屿
在火辣辣的热带太阳底下
because soon the island,
under the blazing tropical sun,
将热的难以忍受
will be intolerably hot.
除非她能翻越这座石头山
Unless she can get over
this rocky wall,
否则她将在她的壳里被烤熟
she will be baked in her shell.
这个致命的障碍物在每个繁殖季节都要了很多受害者的性命
This lethal obstacle course claims
many victims every nesting season.
一次的滑落可能会带来灾难
Just one slip could bring disaster.
她是如此地接近
She was so close.
但不代表着错过了所有的机会
But all may not be lost.
涨潮了
The tide is turning.
如果她被楔形物困住的话
她将会被淹死
If she is completely wedged,
she will drown.
但是上升的海水有可能将抬升助她脱困
But there is a chance that the
rising water could lift her free.
对于这个繁殖季节而言
For this breeding season,
他作为母亲的义务已经达成
her obligations as a mother
are over.
他将永远不会见到她的孩子们
She will never see her babies.
他们过两个月才能得以诞生，假如他们可以的话
They won't hatch for another
two months and, when they do,
他们必须在没有她的帮忙的情况下生存
they will have to survive
without any help from her.
其他的父母必须在孩子身旁形影不离地照顾着
Other parents have to remain close
to their young at all times
来保护他们远离危险
to protect them from danger.
加拿大的阿尔伯塔  一只水牛
A mother bison in Alberta, Canada.
他的小牛有一个星期多大
Her calf is little more
than a week old.
狼群们  很明智地  选择了最简单的目标
Wolves, sensibly,
select the easiest targets.
小牛们
The calves.
所以水牛母亲们尝试让小牛们呆在牛群的中间
So bison mothers try to keep their
young in the centre of the herd
在那里他们最安全
where they are safest.
但是当牛群在奔跑时就不完全是如此了
But that is not always possible
when the herd is on the run.
追逐或将持续二十五千米
The chase may continue
for 25km
狼群们尝试着追直到目标精疲力竭
as the wolves try to run
their targets to exhaustion.
狼群做出了他们的选择
The wolves make their choice.
她独自一人  但对于保护小牛却毫无畏惧
She is on her own, but she's
fearless in protecting her calf.
通过保持接近小牛
By keeping her calf close,
她成功地防御住了两个攻击者
she manages to hold off
both of her attackers.
但是另一只加了进来而她无法同时与三只进行搏斗
But another wolf joins in
and she can't fight three.
现在狼群们协作耗尽她的体力
Now the wolves work together
to wear her down.
森林就在不远处
The forest is not far off.
如果母亲和小牛能到达树林里
If mother and calf
can reach the trees,
他们或许就可以躲避狼群们保持足够长的距离
重新加入牛群里
they may be able to dodge the wolves
for long enough to re-join the herd.
但是攻击是如此的无情
But the attack is so unrelenting,
他们无法冲刺寻找遮蔽处
they can't make a dash for cover.
狼群们逐渐累了下来
The wolves are beginning to tire.
母亲看到了突破口
She sees an opportunity
to make a break for it.
再一次地  她阻挡了狼群的路径
Once again,
she blocks the wolves' path.
狼群在树林里跟丢了他们
And the wolves lose them
amongst the trees.
但是狼仍然是永远存在的隐患
But the wolves remain
an ever-present threat.
嚎叫
HOWLING
而这很可能将不会是
And this is unlikely to be
the last time
母亲必须为了小牛而战斗的最后一次
that this mother will
have to fight for her calf.
父母的责任看起来似乎是天生的
The duties of parenthood
may seem to be instinctive,
但仍然有需要学习的技巧
but there are some skills
that have to be learned.
一群哈奴曼叶猴 五十只 生活在印度的一个悬崖上
A troop of Hanuman langurs, 50
strong, living on a cliff in India.
这是一个巨大的家庭
有着各个年纪的成员
This is one huge family,
with members of all ages.
但只有一只成年雄性
But there is only one adult male.
他脸上的伤疤是他暴力过去的证明
His scarred face is
evidence of his violent past.
它是所有这些年轻人的父亲
He is the father
of all these youngsters.
对于这个初为父亲的刀疤脸而言
任务很少而且有不少好处
Fatherhood for Scarface
has few duties and many perks.
他获得了来自雌性很多的注意力
He gets plenty of attention
from the females...
作为父母采取了放任自由的方式
..and takes a somewhat hands-off
approach to parenting.
但是他的保护给了他的家庭
But his protection gives his family
成员们所需要用来成长和学习的
the safety and the space they need
安全和空间
to grow and learn.
这个群体最新加入的成员
The newest addition to the troop.
这个婴儿完全依靠着他的母亲而她溺爱着他
The baby is totally dependent
on his mother and she dotes on him.
但要想成为一个好母亲需要练习
But becoming a good mother
takes practice.
而一个年轻的雌性，未来的母亲
And a young female, a future parent,
正通过与其他母亲的婴儿玩耍学习者
is learning by playing mum
with someone else's baby.
她看起来含情脉脉
She seems affectionate enough.
这对于这个保姆而言是个宝贵的经验
This is valuable experience
for the baby-sitter.
现在她开始与他玩耍
But now she starts to play with it.
事情很快就失控了
And things get quickly out of hand.
婴儿尖叫
BABY SQUEALS
她看起来像要把婴儿从身上摇下来
She seems to want to
shake off the baby.
看起来需要增援了
Rescue, it seems, is at hand.
但这不是这个婴儿的母亲
But this isn't the baby's mother,
而是个经验甚至比前一只还要匮乏的另一个初学者
it's another learner with even
less of a clue than the last.
最终  婴儿真正的母亲
Eventually, the baby's real mother
觉得游戏进行的够久了
decides that this game has
gone on long enough.
她救下了她的婴儿并给与了一些正确的母亲的照料
She rescues her baby and gives it
some proper motherly care.
或许她容忍着这些未来或将成为保姆的行为
Perhaps she tolerates the behaviour
of these would-be baby-sitters
的原因是他们是近亲
because they're close relatives.
如此多的雌性在这个悬崖边聚集在一起不可避免的
So many females gathered together
on this cliff inevitably attract
吸引了敌对成年雄性的注意力
the attention of a rival adult male.
他的目标是打败刀疤脸并将他的妻子们抢过来
His aim is to defeat Scarface
and take over his females.
他带着一群被遗弃的单身汉上阵
He leads a group of outcast
bachelors into battle.
刀疤脸注意到了他
Scarface spots them.
刀疤脸没有输的余地 因为一旦他输了
He has everything to lose because,
if the bachelors defeat him,
他们将不仅仅夺走他的雌性们
they won't just take his females,
还会把孩子杀掉
they will kill his babies.
单身汉尝试着占领高地从而发动进攻
The bachelors try to reach the
high ground to launch their attack.
刀疤脸警告他们别靠近
Scarface warns them to keep
their distance,
但单身汉们持续前进
but the bachelors
continue their advance.
凶狠的吼叫
HARSH BARKS
刀疤脸磨着牙齿表示他已经动真格了
Scarface grinds his teeth to show
he means business.
但是单身汉领袖爬到了悬崖的顶端
But the bachelor leader
reaches the cliff top
同样磨牙进行回击
and grinds his teeth in response.
如果刀疤脸输掉了这场战斗
他将失去他的后代
If Scarface loses this battle,
he will lose his legacy.
进攻的时刻到了
Time to strike.
他瞄准了单身的领袖
He targets the bachelor leader.
叽叽叫
SCREECHING
刀疤脸获得了胜利
Scarface has won.
他回来受到了英雄般的欢迎
And he returns to a hero's welcome.
但这只是一个短暂的喘息
But it's only a temporary respite.
对于像刀疤脸一样的煞星而言
For a male langur like Scarface,
亲子关系既简单又危险
parenthood is simple, but dangerous.
她阻击了单身汉们并且拯救了他的后代
He has banished the bachelors
and saved his offspring,
至少到目前为止而言
for now at least.
其他的父母要想成功则需要专心致志
Success for other parents requires
total dedication.
一只非洲卷尾鸡
An African drongo.
她必须为她三颗蛋找到遮蔽酷热光线的地方
She has to shade her three eggs
from the scorching heat of the sun.
一旦小鸡孵化
As soon as the chicks hatch,
她将立刻与他们形成牢不可破的关系
she will form an immediate bond
with them that is unbreakable,
无论发生了什么
whatever happens.
经过了数百个小时的孵育后  她第一只小鸡
After hundreds of hours
of incubation...her first chick.
现在辛苦的工作真正开始了
Now the hard work really begins
因为新孵出的小鸡需要食物
because the newly hatched
chick needs food.
距离剩余两只加入进来不会太久了
It won't be long before one mouth
is joined by two more
这只小鸡将需要一起分享母亲带回来的食物
and this chick will then have to
share what the female brings back.
或者他会吗
Or will it?
小鸡排除着任何有可能的竞争
The chick is getting rid of any
competition.
他想要母亲只注意他一个
It wants its mother's sole
attention.
喂食时间
Feeding time.
有什么变化  但是什么呢
Something has changed. But what?
疯狂的啾啾叫
FRANTIC CHIRRUPING
她小鸡明亮橙色的嘴
The sight of her chick's bright
orange mouth
要求她带来更多的食物
demands that she brings more food.
蛋几乎和小鸡一样重
The egg weighs
almost as much as the chick.
这就像把一块石头推上山坡
It's like pushing a boulder uphill.
小鸡在他的背部上有空心的构造
能够帮助他支撑这个重量
The chick has a hollow in its back
that helps it manoeuvre its load.
母亲的后代被减少到了只剩这只小鸡
The mother's brood has been reduced
to just this one chick
现在他获得了她全部的注意力了
and it now has her total attention.
当她没有外出寻找食物的时候
她将小鸡藏了起来
When she's not away gathering food,
she shades the chick.
但任何时候他需要食物的时候她将立刻做出反应
And she responds instantly
whenever it demands to be fed.
超过三个星期内每天如此
Every day for over three weeks,
她带来数打顿饭
she brings it dozens of meals.
她的小鸡看起来从不停止进食  或者成长
Her chick never seems to stop
eating, or stop growing.
附近还有一个卷尾鸡的巢
There is another drongo's nest
nearby
里头有三只小鸡
and that has three chicks in it.
但他们看起来不太像她的东西
But they don't look quite
the same as hers.
那是因为她正哺育着陌生人
That is because she is raising
an alien...
杜鹃的幼鸟
the chick of a cuckoo.
杜鹃把他们的蛋生到其他鸟类的巢里
Cuckoos lay their eggs
in the nests of other birds
把辛苦的养育工作留给其他人
and leave the hard labour of rearing
the chick to someone else.
杜鹃的蛋和卷尾鸟的蛋如此相似
The cuckoo's egg matched
the drongo's egg so perfectly
以至于收养的母亲也被欺骗了
that this foster mother
has been completely deceived.
在其他的卷尾巢里
小鸟们即将起步
Over at the other drongo nest,
the chicks are now fledging.
他们的父母们成功地
Their parents have succeeded
创造了他们的下一代
in producing their very own
next generation,
而她养育了一只怪物
while she has raised a monster.
她的爱
是盲目的Her love is blind.
回到刚果
Back in the Congo,
倭黑猩猩母亲对她婴儿的照料持续着
the mother bonobo's long-term
commitment to her baby continues.
今天 她正展示着
Today, she's demonstrating
如何在距离地三十公尺的空中建造一张床
the tricky art of making
a bed 30 feet above the ground,
来为午间的小睡做准备
in preparation for a midday siesta.
教学完毕
她很好地使用了这个手工作品
Lesson over,
she puts her handiwork to good use.
对于一个忙绿的母亲而言
额外的午睡总是很受欢迎的
For a busy mother,
an extra nap is always welcome.
但婴儿看起来很无聊
But Baby seems bored.
他的母亲仍然是他世界的中心
His mother is still
the centre of his world
和他最欢的玩伴
and his favourite playmate.
她尝试着无视他
但是他不会因此而消停
She tries to ignore him,
but he won't be put off.
最终 她放弃了
Eventually, she gives in.
整个家庭都在行动当中
The whole family is on the move.
在倭黑猩猩的社会里
In bonobo society,
知识一代又一代地被传递下去
knowledge is passed down
from one generation to the next.
他们的母亲即将向年轻人展示
The mothers are going to show
their youngsters
森林里最重要的地方之一
one of the most important places in
the forest.
一个生长着百合花的特别的池塘
A special pool
where water lilies grow.
水百合含有对健康重要的矿物质
Water lilies contain minerals
important for health,
倭黑猩猩们无法从别处获得
and the bonobos can't get them
anywhere else.
孩子们通过观察母亲学习该吃什么东西
Baby learns
what to eat by watching Mum.
她把百合茎分给了他们
And she shares
the lily stalks with him.
她已经向他们展示到哪里获取重要的食物补充
She's shown him where to get
an important supplement to his diet
他甚至不用弄湿他的脚
and he didn't even
have to get his feet wet.
她将继续帮助他认识这片森林
She will continue to help him
to learn about the forest
再过五年
在他家庭的保护下
for another five years,
within the protection of his family.
但是很少有年轻人能在在像这样安全的环境下长大
But few youngsters are raised
in such a secure environment.
这只年轻斑马诞生的地方正逐渐变得干燥
The land where this young zebra
was born is drying out.
他的母亲必须带领着他横渡河流来获取新鲜的青草
Its mother must lead it across
the river to reach fresh grazing.
她面临着关键的选择
She faces a critical decision.
从哪里跨越过去
Where to cross.
她六个星期大的小马驹的生命由她决定
The life of her six-week-old foal
hangs on her decision.
不光光是鳄鱼形成了威胁
It's not just crocodiles
that pose a threat.
从这里跨越太危险了
Crossing here is too dangerous.
在较远的下流处   或许有一个更适合穿越的地方
Further downstream, perhaps
this is a better place to cross.
那里猎食者比较少  但流速快
There are fewer predators,
but the river is fast
还有危险的急流
and has treacherous rapids.
这是一次艰难的选择
It's a difficult decision.
一旦母亲做出了决定
同时做出了小马驹的决定
Once a mother commits herself,
she commits her foal,
她将对此爱莫能助
and there will be nothing
she can do to help it.
水流如此之强
以至于带着他们顺流而下
The current is so strong,
it carries them downstream
穿越坏脾气的河马群
through the territory of
ill-tempered hippos...
前往危险的湍流里
..and towards the rapids.
断断续续的叫声
STACCATO BARKING
穿越这里的决定被证明是个好想法
The decision to cross here
has proved to be a good one,
但仅仅是这次
but only just.
母亲引领者小马驹
This mother has led her foal
度过了他年轻的生命里最危险的时光
through the most dangerous
moment of its young life.
通过保证小马驹的安全
By keeping her foal safe,
他通过了作为母亲重要的测试
she has passed
this critical test of motherhood.
东非 安博塞利的黎明
Dawn in Amboseli, East Africa.
一个象群
A family of elephants.
年轻人正安稳地睡着觉
The young are sleeping peacefully,
被一堵由母亲们和祖母们
surrounded by a protective wall
所组成的包围墙所包围
of mothers and grandmothers.
每个早上带领着小象朝着自立更进一步
Each morning brings the calves
a little closer to independence.
他们或许是成功的父母
They may be successful parents,
但是对于他们在早晨唤醒年轻人仍有困难
but they still have trouble getting
the youngsters up in the morning.
在这个族群里有三代人  家庭成功的证明
There are three generations in this
herd, proof of the family's success.
他们找到了一个年长雄性的骸骨
They have found
the bones of an old female.
即使是幼儿们也被他们祖先的骨头给吸引了
Even the babies are intrigued
by these relics of their ancestors.
我们当然无从得知他们在想什么
We can't, of course,
know what they're thinking,
但是他们碰这些骨头的时候有种敏锐的感觉
but there is a delicacy in the way
they touch these bones,
这暗示着他们有些特殊的关系在里面
which suggests that they have some
special relevance.
或许大象有一种共同历史的感觉
Perhaps elephants have a sense
of a shared history.
这种经验似乎带领着他们彼此更近了
The experience seems to bring them
even closer together.
兽群里的每只动物都属于某个家庭谱系
Every animal in the herd belongs
to a family line
可以延伸追溯到数不清的代数之前
that stretches back through
numberless generations.
每只能在这里
And each is here
因为他们的祖先全都是生存游戏的胜者
because their ancestors were
all winners in the game of life.
某只个体动物成功的机会
An individual animal's
chance of success
根据他的种类而不同
varies according to its kind,
和他们的父母施与它们身上的爱
and to the care lavished upon it
by its parents.
大多数的年轻倭黑猩猩都能存活
Most young bonobos survive
childhood.
但最终  每个都必须找出属于自己通往世界的道路
But, eventually, each will have
to find its own way in the world.
他可能需要同伴一同面对危险
It may need allies to face
up to danger.
他将需要寻找自己在社会上的位置
It will have to find its own
place in society.
它将上演求爱的游戏
It will play the mating game...
..成为一个父母....
..become a parent...
..最终通过留下自己的后代
..and eventually achieve
a form of immortality
获得一种形式上的不朽
by leaving its own offspring.
不曾有过两段完全相同的生命旅程
No two journeys through life
are ever the same...
每个就像手指印一样独一无二
..each is as unique as a
fingerprint.
母亲的生命是成功的
This mother's life has been
a success.
但对于每一个新一代而言  旅途将全部重新开始
But for each new generation, the
journey will begin all over again.
这就是生命伟大的故事
It's life's great story.
倭黑猩猩生活在地球上最人迹罕至的地方
Bonobos live in the most
impenetrable forest on Earth -
刚果
the Congo.
卡梅隆。罗夫。斯坦曼
Cameraman, Rolf Steinmann,
在世界上某些最壮观的开阔土地上工作
has worked in some of the world's
great open landscapes,
但不曾有地方如此
but never anywhere like this.
他的愿望是拍摄倭黑猩猩
His hope is to film scenes
of the bonobos' lives
之前从未被捕捉到的生活情景
that have never been captured before
并且或许能对我们的过去一窥究竟
and perhaps gain a glimpse
into our own past.
随同的有摄像助手  艾德 安德森
Accompanied by camera assistant,
Ed Anderson,
他们深入到非洲雨林里旅行
they journey deep
into the African rainforest.
尽管到探索营地有六英里
Despite a 16—mile walk to the
research camp,
洛夫的情绪很高昂
Rolf's spirits are high.
这真的很令人激动并且我认为
It's really exciting and I think...
毫无疑问这是我走到的最偏远的地方
it's definitely the most remote
location I have ever walked to.
Luikotale探索营地将会是接下来七星期里他们的家
The LuiKotale research camp will be
their home for the next seven weeks.
他们前往到森林里
They head out into the forest
穿着面罩  以免把人类病毒传染给了倭黑猩猩们
wearing facemasks to protect
the bonobos from human diseases.
他们为了追踪倭黑猩猩徒步行走超过十二英里
They hike over 12 miles
following the bonobos
并且最终 罗夫首次看到了
and, eventually,
Rolf gets his first view.
我会说   这是相当特殊的一天
It was a pretty special day,
I would say.
这是我第一个倭黑猩猩日
That was my first bonobo day.
这毫无疑问很令人叹为观止
It was absolutely breathtaking,
看着他们的脸
looking into their faces,
照看婴儿们
seeing the babies.
我的意思是  你可以确实感受到他们是我们的近亲
I mean, you can really feel
that they're close relatives to us.
我的意思是  就好像你被一群非常小的人类包围了起来
I mean, it feels like you are
surrounded by very little humans.
但他很快就发现这样好的天气并不典型
But he quickly discovers
that such a good day isn't typical.
大声叹气
HE SIGHS HEAVILY
植物太多了  我看不清楚
There is so much vegetation,
I can't get a clear view,
完全不可能
it's totally impossible.
这片丛林的茂密程度带来了另外一个问题
And the very density of this forest
creates other filming problems.
我们正从森林里走回来
We're walking back to
camp from the forest,
现在是下午三点三十分   这并非拍摄效果  毫无疑问是昏暗
it's 3.30pm, this is not a camera
effect, it really is this dark.
当太阳尚未出现的时候
When the sun isn't out,
有时感觉就像夜里一样
it feels like the middle of the
night sometimes.
艾德和罗夫的困难不断在增加者
Ed and Rolf's difficulties
just continue to mount.
倭黑猩猩进入到了森立最深处，最茂密的地方
The bonobos went into the deepest,
densest part of the forest,
要跟踪他们真的很困难
it's really hard to follow them.
高达百分之九十的湿度正给相机带来麻烦
The 90% humidity is causing
trouble for the camera.
更糟的是  他们很快就遭遇到了其他森林的住户
And worse, they soon encounter some
of the other forest inhabitants.
这里全是蚂蚁
It's all full of ants here.
我没法带着这个背包穿越这里
I can't get through there with
the big backpack.
到处都是蚂蚁！
Ants are everywhere!
啊蚂蚁到处咬我
Ah, they're biting me everywhere.
他们总想要鲜肉
They always want to
get to the flesh.
不  你不可以进入那里
No, you don't get in there.
(和谐)  他们那里都咬
BLEEP! They are biting everywhere!
啊 （和谐） 这一点都不有趣  真的很痛  走开 哦我的老天
Ah, BLEEP! It's not really fun, it's
really painful. Go away. Ah. Oh, God.
我必须从这里出去
I just have to get out of this.
哇
Wow.
我们如何除掉这些白蚁呢
How should we get rid of
all these termites?
我意思是  那很糟糕
I mean, that is serious.
热量和湿度
The heat and humidity,
这个跋山涉水的旅程和昆虫
比罗夫所担心的还要更糟
the trekking and the insects
are worse than Rolf had feared.
但带给他最大的挫折是
But causing him most distress
几乎没法拍摄那些倭黑猩猩们
is hardly ever being able to
film the bonobos.
你看到的东西里面有九成没法被拍摄
90% of the things you see
you can't film.
如此昏暗   植被又如此之多
It's so dark,
there's so much vegetation
动物们总是在错误的地点
and the animals are always
in the wrong spot.
我觉得这变得越来越让人沮丧了
It is pretty much as frustrating
as it gets, I think.
你真的必须学习如何面对这些挫折
You really have to learn to deal
with all the frustration
变成类似于禅师那样  并且控制你的情绪
and become some kind of Zen master
and suppress your emotions.
否则你将这里将冒着相当高的疯掉的可能性
Otherwise you face a high risk here
to get insane.
*我是摄影人*
I am the lucky cameraman.
*我是幸运的摄影人*
三个星期的跋山涉水
Three weeks of trekking
最终猩猩家庭出现了  在空旷地里
and finally the bonobo family
appear, briefly, in the open.
（就在那里 倭黑猩猩在一根圆木头上 彻底放松着
(There the bonobos are on a log,
totally relaxed.
（我拍摄到的到目前为止最棒的镜头  太惊人了）
(I've got my best shots so far,
it's amazing!)
但是倭黑猩猩很快再次消失
But the bonobos soon disappear again
又回到了每天艰苦的丛林生活里了
and it's back
to the daily grind of forest life.
嗡嗡
BUZZING
啊 这些汗蜂要让我抓狂了
Ah, these sweat bees make me crazy.
他们开始拍摄时的乐观态度已经无影无踪了
The optimism with which they began
this shoot is long gone.
今天到目前为止我们已经前进了二十五公里
Today, we've already
walked 25km
穿过了一些最浓密，最厚的森林
through some of the densest,
thickest jungle so far.
我们没拍到任何一张倭黑猩猩的镜头
We didn't get a single
shot of the bonobos.
是的 经常这里就像个海军训练的营地
Yeah, it sometimes
feels like a boot camp here.
总有一天....你只想忘记这些...
Some days...you just want to forget.
这种经历让人精疲力竭
The experience is simply exhausting.
最终  完美的瞬间
Finally, the perfect moment.
就在我们白天第一次扎营的时候
Right when we get our first
nesting in the daytime,
真的相当漂亮的角度   完美的位置
really beautiful angle,
perfect position,
相机停止了运行
the camera stopped working
现在我们必须返回营地  离开倭黑猩猩们
and now we have to go back to camp,
leaving the bonobos,
希望我们能让相机重新工作
and hope that we can make
the camera work again.
是的  我们真的不知道该说什么了
Yeah, don't know really what to say.
等到拿到新相机的时候
By the time they've got
a new camera,
倭黑猩猩们都彻底消失了
the bonobos have
completely disappeared.
保罗 保罗 保罗 这是艾德
保罗 保罗  这是艾德
Paul, Paul, Paul, this is Ed.
Paul, Paul, this is Ed.
保罗进来
Come in, Paul.
我们听不见他们
We can't hear them,
我们找不到任何踪迹
we can't find any tracks,
因此看起来不是很乐观
so it doesn't look very promising.
罗夫能对艰苦环境免疫
Rolf is hardened
to tough conditions,
但无法承受拍摄不到清晰照片的挫折
but not the frustration of
so rarely getting a clear shot.
四天以后
Four days later,
倭黑猩猩们被定位
the bonobos have been located,
但他们仍然处于移动当中
but they're on the move.
他们正朝着北方前进
They're heading north
因此他们将有相当大进入到沼泽范围的可能性
so there's a good chance that they
go into the swamps
因此我们只能观察
and so we just speculate
朝着沼泽跑过去
and run towards the swamps
或许我能在那里发现他们
and perhaps we find them there.
在如此多的失望之后
After so much disappointment,
罗夫的艾德决心找到他们
Rolf and Ed are determined
to find them.
与胜算反常 相当不可思议地
Quite against the odds,
他们的决心获得了回报
their determination pays off.
罗夫捕捉到了第一张照片
Rolf captures the first-ever images
倭黑猩猩采集百合花的照片
of a family of bonobos
harvesting lilies.
一个仿佛窥视到我们过去的场景
A scene that feels much
like a glimpse into our own past.
这就是罗夫所希望的一切
It's everything Rolf had hoped for.
在这片土地上   我们能够办到简直是荒唐的 这是荒唐的
In this terrain, it's ridiculous that
we made it, that is ridiculous!
要想拍摄是不可能的
It's impossible to film that,
这简直就是不可能的  而我们办到了！
it's simply impossible
and we filmed it!
我难以置信  太棒了！
I can't believe it, it's so good!
我们的生活或许和我们最接近的亲戚看起来有许多不同
Our lives may seem very different
from those of our closest relatives,
但是在表面之下
我们仍然共同面对着
but beneath the surface,
we still share the same challenges
每一个动物在他的一生中所需要面对的挑战
that every animal faces in its
own Life Story.
未来花园纪录片爱好者制作出品  感谢您的支持